<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
      xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
      xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
      xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
      xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <info>
    <title>Akeeba Remote CLI User's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Nicholas</firstname><othername>K.</othername><surname>Dionysopoulos</surname></personname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Akeeba Ltd</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>

    <pubdate>October 2018</pubdate>
  </info>

  <chapter>
    <title>Welcome</title>

    <section xml:id="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>Remote CLI is a powerful command-line script which allows you to
      automate your backups (including download backup archives) with Akeeba
      Backup for Joomla! or WordPress; or Akeeba Solo. It is designed for
      power users and system administrators who want to automate these
      backup-related tasks. It uses our remote JSON API, which means that you
      can install the script on one machine (even your own PC) and control any
      number of sites, across different hosts, remotely.</para>

      <para>The script is shipped as a PHAR file. This is an executable PHP
      package which can be used with PHP 5.5.0 or later (PHP 7.0 or 7.1
      recommended). The script is available for download free of charge from
      our site.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="using-remotecli">
    <title>Using Remote CLI</title>

    <section xml:id="usage">
      <title>Usage</title>

      <bridgehead>Using the PHAR file</bridgehead>

      <para>The traditional way to use Remote CLI is as a command line script
      running on your machine.</para>

      <para>Remote CLI requires a command line version of PHP (a.k.a. PHP-CLI)
      to be installed on your machine. In the command line below, please
      substitute php with the full path to your PHP CLI executable file. On
      most Linux and Mac OS X systems, you don't need to specify a path, just
      <command>php</command> will do as the executable file is already in the
      path. On Windows, however, you most likely need to specify a full
      path.</para>

      <tip>
        <para>The PHP project provides <link
        xlink:href="http://windows.php.net/download/">an installer of PHP for
        Windows</link> which can install PHP for you and place the php.exe
        binary in your path. For sanity's sake, we recommend you to install
        PHP in <filename>c:\PHP</filename> and put
        <filename>remote.phar</filename> in there as well. This is the easiest
        way to be perfectly sure where everything is installed!</para>
      </tip>

      <important>
        <para>Remote CLI requires PHP 5.5 with the optional "phar" extension
        installed and activated. This is the default setup of PHP in most
        cases.</para>
      </important>

      <para>After downloading remote.phar (the Remote CLI executable PHP
      archive) from our site you can use Remote CLI from the command line of
      your operating system with a command like this:</para>

      <programlisting>php remote.phar <replaceable>actionName</replaceable> --host=<replaceable>hostName</replaceable> --secret=<replaceable>secretKey</replaceable> <replaceable>[options]</replaceable></programlisting>

      <para><replaceable>php</replaceable> is the path to your PHP CLI
      exectuable. If this is not in your path or you are not sure, please ask
      your host or your system administrator.</para>

      <bridgehead>Using the Dockerized version</bridgehead>

      <para>If you are using Docker you can make use of the Dockerized version
      of Remote CLI:</para>

      <programlisting>docker run --rm akeebaltd/remotecli <replaceable>actionName</replaceable> --host=<replaceable>hostName</replaceable> --secret=<replaceable>secretKey</replaceable> <replaceable>[options]</replaceable></programlisting>

      <para>The Dockerized version is self-contained, using the latest version
      of PHP at the time we build the container image. It's much simpler to
      use since it does not require installing or configuring anything on your
      host machine. Moreover, it's <emphasis>self-updating</emphasis>. The
      command line above always tries to use the latest version of Remote CLI
      we have published in Docker Hub.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>There's a caveat. You can NOT use the Dockerized version with
        local servers i.e. anything which resolves to an IP address only
        routable by the host machine. If you want to try our Remote CLI
        locally you have to use the PHAR file.</para>
      </warning>

      <bridgehead>What are all these options?</bridgehead>

      <para><replaceable>hostName</replaceable> is the URL to your site's
      root, without a trailing slash, e.g. <uri>http://www.example.com</uri>.
      If you are using Akeeba Backup for WordPress the
      <replaceable>hostName</replaceable> must also include the path to Akeeba
      Backup's index.php file tasked with handling the JSON API, e.g.
      <uri>http://www.example.com/wp-content/plugins/akeebabackupwp/app/remote.php</uri>
      where http://www.example.com is the URL to your site and akeebabackupwp
      is the name of the folder where the Akeeba Backup for WordPress plugin
      is installed.</para>

      <para><replaceable>secretKey</replaceable> is the Secret Key you have
      defined in the component Options (Akeeba Backup for Joomla!) or the
      System Configuration (Akeeba Backup for WordPress, Akeeba Solo) page of
      the backup application.</para>

      <para>The options which are required for each action are described in
      the <link linkend="options">Options</link> chapter of this
      documentation.</para>

      <para>For practical examples, or if you want to find out how to automate
      backing up and downloading the backups of your site, please consult the
      <link linkend="walkthrough">Walkthrough</link> chapter.</para>

      <para><replaceable>actionName</replaceable> can be one of:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>license</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Displays the license of the software and quits.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>test</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Tests whether Remote CLI can connect to your site. If it can
            not, it will tell you why.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>backup</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Performs a backup. It can (optionally) download the backup
            archive and delete it from the server afterwards.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>download</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Downloads a backup archive and can optionally delete it from
            the server afterwards</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>deletefile</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Delete backup archives from the server</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>delete</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Deletes backup archives and the associated backup record
            from the server</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>listbackups</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Lists the latest backup records</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>profiles</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Lists the profile IDs and descriptions</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>backupinfo</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Shows detailed information about a backup record</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>upgrade</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Upgrades Akeeba Backup on the server, if there is an update
            available</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <tip>
        <para>You can also use the legacy
        <option>--action=<replaceable>actionName</replaceable></option> syntax
        for backwards compatibility with version 1.x.</para>
      </tip>

      <warning>
        <para>Before you can use Remote CLI with your site, you will need to
        enable the remote API in Akeeba Backup / Akeeba Solo. In order to do
        that, go to Akeeba Backup / Akeeba Solo and click on either the
        <guibutton>Options</guibutton> button in the toolbar (Akeeba Backup
        for Joomla!) or the <guibutton>System Configuration</guibutton> button
        towards the bottom of the page (Akeeba Backup for WordPress, Akeeba
        Solo). You will have to set <guilabel>Enable front-end and remote
        backup</guilabel> to Yes. You will also need to supply a
        <guilabel>Secret Key</guilabel> of your liking. This is the password
        to connect to your site over Akeeba Backup's Remote API. Due to
        several issues which have to do with server configuration, we strongly
        recommend using only alphanumeric characters (a-z, A-Z, 0-9), dash and
        underscore in your Secret Key. Other characters may lead to inability
        to connect to your site. Use something long and complex.</para>
      </warning>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="options">
      <title>Options</title>

      <para>Under any circumstances you can append <option>-m</option> or
      <option>--machine-readable</option> to the end of the command line to
      instruct Remote CLI to use a machine-readable output format. If you omit
      it, a human-readable format will be used instead (default).</para>

      <para>Using the option <option>--nocolor</option> will skip the
      generation of color escape sequences. The default behaviour of Remote
      CLI is to color-code its output for easier reading. However, some
      terminal emulators, like Windows' command prompt application, do not
      support them and display them as verbatim text. This can be confusing,
      therefore the use of <option>--nocolor</option> is strongly
      recommended.</para>

      <para>Moreover, you can specify the <option>--license</option> parameter
      to display the text of the GNU General Public License version 3, under
      which the software is distributed. In this case, the action and all
      options will be silently ignored. This has the same effect as specifying
      the license command.</para>

      <para>Each action can be used with one or several options. Some of them
      are mandatory for the correct operation of Remote CLI. The following
      sections detail the parameters which can be used with each option. All
      actions require the following mandatory options:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>host</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The URL to your site's root, without a trailing slash, e.g.
            <uri>http://www.example.com</uri> Please note that if your site is
            located in a subdirectory, you have to give the full path to the
            subdirectory, e.g. <uri>http://www.example.com/joomla</uri></para>

            <para>If you are using Akeeba Backup for WordPress the
            <replaceable>hostName</replaceable> must also include the path to
            Akeeba Backup's index.php file tasked with handling the JSON API,
            e.g.
            <uri>http://www.example.com/wp-content/plugins/akeebabackupwp/app/index.php</uri>
            where http://www.example.com is the URL to your site and
            akeebabackupwp is the name of the folder where the Akeeba Backup
            for WordPress plugin is installed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>secret</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The secret key, as defined in Akeeba Backup's component
            parameters. In order to access it in the component, please log in
            to your site's back-end, go to Components, Akeeba Backup and click
            on the Component Parameters button. Make sure the Enable front-end
            and remote backup option is enabled. Right below it, you will find
            the Secret Key field.</para>

            <important>
              <para>We strongly advise you to use only lower and upper case
              Latin letters and numbers (a-z, A-Z, 0-9) in your secret word,
              as many servers will refuse to work with secret words containing
              special characters.</para>
            </important>

            <important>
              <para>If you are using sh404SEF make sure you have upgraded to
              the latest release. Older versions conflicted with Akeeba
              Backup's remote API feature and will cause Remote CLI to report
              a JSON decoding error. No support will be provided for this
              error. The only workaround is to upgrade your copy of sh404SEF
              (which is a good idea anyway, as the older versions also
              contained potential security vulnerabilities).</para>
            </important>

            <important>
              <para>Some SEF and security components will corrupt or block the
              request to Akeeba Backup's Remote API. In this case you will
              most likely get a "JSON decoding error". If this happens you may
              have to instruct your component to ignore com_akeeba or allow
              full access to the
              <uri>http://www.example.com/index.php?option=com_akeeba&amp;view=json</uri>
              URL. If unsure, please consult with the developer of your SEF or
              security component.</para>
            </important>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Below you can find the options required by each command:</para>

      <bridgehead>test</bridgehead>

      <para>No extra options are used</para>

      <bridgehead>backup</bridgehead>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>profile</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The numeric profile ID you want take a backup with. If it is
            not specified, a backup with the default profile (#1) will be
            taken. Please see the profiles command for an easy way to list
            profile names and IDs.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>description</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An optional description of your backup. Put it in double
            quotes, i.e. <option>--description="My backup
            description"</option>. If not specified, the default backup
            description (the one with the date and time of the backup) will be
            used by Akeeba Backup automatically.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>comment</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>An optional backup comment. Put it in double quotes, i.e.
            <option>--comment="My backup comment"</option>. If not specified,
            no comment will be stored with your backup.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>download</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>If you specify <option>--download</option> or
            <option>-d</option>, the produced backup archive will be
            downloaded to your computer. In this case, please refer to the
            next section for its required parameters. You can also specify
            <option>--delete</option> or <option>-D</option> together with
            <option>--download</option> / <option>-d</option> in order to
            delete the backup archive after it has been downloaded to your
            PC.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <bridgehead>download</bridgehead>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>id</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The numeric backup ID to download (see listbackups). Note:
            when you use the --download or -d switch with the backup action
            you must not use this option. In all other cases, this option is
            mandatory.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>dlmode</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Can be one of http, chunk or curl</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>http</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>instructs Remote CLI to download the backup archive
                  through HTTP, similar to what you get by clicking the
                  download links in the "Manage Backups" (formerly "Administer
                  Backup Files") page of Akeeba Backup. Even though it is the
                  simplest method, it may cause corrupted downloads of backup
                  archives over 10-20Mb on most shared hosts.</para>

                  <para>Files are transferred unencrypted with this method.
                  You are advised to only use this if your server is using
                  HTTPS or with JPS (encrypted) archives only.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>chunk</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>works similarly to http, but is designed to work with
                  larger backup archives. It tries to download 1Mb at a time,
                  in order to work around server restrictions on HTTP
                  download. However, on a few shared hosts this will cause the
                  download to fail with a timeout error, memory outage error
                  or an Internal Server Error (HTTP 500 error).</para>

                  <para>If you have used an <option>--encapsulation</option>
                  parameter other than RAW all data is transferred encrypted
                  with this method. This is the recommended method for servers
                  which offer neither HTTPS nor FTPS/SFTP <emphasis>as long as
                  you use an <option>--encapsulation</option> parameter other
                  than RAW</emphasis>.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>curl</term>

                <listitem>
                  <para>is the recommended method and can be used to download
                  the backup archive over FTP, FTPS or SFTP. The only downside
                  is that it needs some configuration (see the dlurl option
                  below).</para>

                  <para>If you are using plain old FTP (not FTPS or SFTP) the
                  files and login credentials are transferred unencrypted. You
                  are advised to never use this method with plain old FTP (not
                  FTPS or SFTP) for security reasons.</para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>dlpath</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Specify the path to save the downloaded file. For example,
            <option>--dlpath="c:\User\Myuser\Downloads"</option> on Windows,
            or <option>--dlpath="/home/myuser/Downloads"</option> on Linux,
            Mac OS X and other UNIX-based operating systems.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>dlurl</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This option is only required if you are using the curl
            download method. In this case, it tells Remote CLI how to connect
            to your site in order to download the backup archives.</para>

            <para>If you are using FTP, you have to specify something like
            <option>--dlurl="ftp://username:password@hostname:port/path/to/output/directory</option></para>

            <para>Username and Password are your FTP username and password.
            Hostname is the FTP server's host name. Port is the numeric TCP/IP
            port (normally it's 21, ask your host). The
            <filename>/path/to/output/directory</filename> is the FTP path to
            yoru output directory. In order to figure out the latter, please
            use FileZilla to connect to your site and navigate to the backup
            output directory (by default that is
            <filename>administrator/components/com_akeeba/backup</filename>).
            Copy the path shown above the right-hand folders pane. That's the
            one you want.</para>

            <para>Example:</para>

            <para><option>--dlurl="ftp://myuser:
            mypassword@ftp.example.com:21/public_html/administrator/components/com_akeeba/backup
            </option></para>

            <important>
              <para>FTP is an unencrypted protocol. It is trivial for a third
              party to snoop into your connection and find the username and
              password you are using to connect to your server. We very
              strongly recommend using SFTP which is a file transfer protocol
              implemented over the very secure SSH remote server connection
              protocol. As a second best, you can use FTPS which is an
              encrypted version of FTP (exactly the same way HTTPS is an
              encrypted version of HTTP).</para>
            </important>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <bridgehead>delete</bridgehead>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>id</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The backup record's ID that you want deleted. Please see
            listbackups below.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <bridgehead>deletefiles</bridgehead>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>id</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The backup record's ID that you want deleted. Please see
            listbackups below.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <bridgehead>profiles</bridgehead>

      <para>This command has no options. It will simply return a list of
      profile IDs and descriptions.</para>

      <bridgehead>listbackups</bridgehead>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>from</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>(Optional) From which record you want to start the listing.
            If not specified, 0 is assumed, showing the top results (latest
            backup records).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>to</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>(Optional) Up to which record you want the listing to go to.
            If not specified, 50 is assumed, therefore showing the latest 50
            backup records.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <bridgehead>backupinfo</bridgehead>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>id</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The backup record's ID whose info you want displayed. Please
            see listbackups above.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <bridgehead>update</bridgehead>

      <para>There are no options. Calling this action will check if an update
      is available and, if there is, will install it automatically on your
      site.</para>

      <important>
        <para>This feature IS NOT available on Joomla!. Extension updates are
        handled by Joomla! itself, not Akeeba Backup. Please refer to
        Joomla!'s documentation for information on updating extensions.</para>
      </important>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuration files</title>

      <para>Akeeba Remote CLI is looking for a personalized configuration
      file. This is true on every Operating System <emphasis>except</emphasis>
      Microsoft Windows which does not make available the necessary
      information to do so.</para>

      <important>
        <para>Configuration files only apply to remote.phar. The Dockerized
        version does not read files from your user folder.</para>
      </important>

      <para>The file is named <filename>.akeebaremotecli</filename> (mind the
      leading dot!) and is located in your home directory. In standard Unix
      notation that would be <filename>~/.akeebaremotecli</filename></para>

      <para>This is a plain text file which follows the INI format. Each
      configuration section can define a set of options which have the same
      effect as being passed to the command line itself. Each section is
      referenced by the <parameter>--host</parameter> command line parameter.
      If you do not define a host, the default entry [akeebaremotecli] will be
      used instead.</para>

      <para>Configuration file example:</para>

      <programlisting>[akeebaremotecli]
host=https://www.example.com
secret=0123456789abcdef0123456789abcdef

[mybackup]
host=https://www.example.com
secret=0123456789abcdef0123456789abcdef
action=backup
profile=2

[example]
host=https://www.example.com
secret=0123456789abcdef0123456789abcdef
profile=3</programlisting>

      <para>Example using the default section (tests the connection):</para>

      <programlisting>remote.phar test</programlisting>

      <para>Example using a named section, without having to specify a command
      (takes a backup with profile #2):</para>

      <programlisting>remote.phar backup --host=mybackup</programlisting>

      <para>Example using a named section, specifying commands and overriding
      options (takes a backup with profile #1);</para>

      <programlisting>remote.phar backup --host=example --profile=1</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="walkthrough">
      <title>Walkthrough</title>

      <para>Below we will see how to get Remote CLI interface your site, make
      sure Akeeba Backup is up to date, run a backup and automatically
      download the backup archive to your PC.</para>

      <para>In this fictional example, the following assumptions are made:
      Your site can be found at <uri>http://www.example.com</uri> and the
      secret word is <option>0Lsp-MjOSLvUL8VuM1h9T2zWfM4EGqMA</option>. The
      backup archives are stored in the default output directory
      (<filename>administrator/components/com_akeeba/backup</filename>). The
      site's FTP host is <uri>ftp.example.com</uri> and its username and
      password are <option>example</option> and <option>test</option>
      respectively. The site is under the <filename>public_html</filename>
      directory. We also assume that the PHP CLI executable is already in your
      path.</para>

      <bridgehead>Connection test</bridgehead>

      <para>We begin by making sure that Remote CLI can access our
      site:</para>

      <programlisting>php remote.phar --action=test --host=http://www.example.com --secret=0Lsp-MjOSLvUL8VuM1h9T2zWfM4EGqMA</programlisting>

      <para>You should see something like this:</para>

      <screen>Akeeba Remote Control CLI svn724 (2011-06-14)
Copyright ©2008-2014 Nicholas K. Dionysopoulos / AkeebaBackup.com
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------
 This program comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY. This is Free Software and you
 are welcome to redistribute it under certain conditions. Use command line
 option --license for details.
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------
Successful connection to site</screen>

      <para>The last line tells you that the connection worked. However, if
      something goes wrong, you might get one of these error messages:</para>

      <para><emphasis>Error 401 - Invalid login credentials</emphasis> : Your
      secret word is wrong. Go to your site's back-end,
      <guimenu>Components</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Akeeba Backup</guimenuitem>,
      click on <guibutton>Component Parameters</guibutton> and enter a secret
      key of your liking. We strongly recommend using only a-z, A-Z and 0-9 to
      work around limitations with some hosts.</para>

      <para><emphasis>Error 503 - Access denied</emphasis>: You forgot to
      enable the remote API or enter a secret word in Akeeba Backup. Go to
      your site's back-end, <guimenu>Components</guimenu>, <guimenuitem>Akeeba
      Backup</guimenuitem>, click on <guibutton>Component
      Parameters</guibutton> and set <guilabel>Enable remote and front-end
      backups</guilabel> to <option>Yes</option>. Then enter a secret key of
      your liking. We strongly recommend using only a-z, A-Z and 0-9 to work
      around limitations with some hosts.</para>

      <para><emphasis>Your server does not seem to be compatible with Remote
      Control</emphasis> : Check that you are using the correct host name,
      including the http/https prefix. Also make sure that Akeeba Backup 3.3.0
      or later is installed and activated. Also note that some SEF and
      security extensions may be blocking the Remote API calls to your site.
      In this case, you won't be able to use Remote CLI.</para>

      <important>
        <para>If your host name, secret key or any other option contains
        non-alphanumeric characters (anything except 0-9, a-z, A-Z, slash,
        backslash, dash, dot and underscore) you MUST enclose the option value
        in double quotes. For example, --secret=ab=gt%6 will not work, but
        --secret="ab=gt%6" will do. If you get connection errors despite
        having set the correct host name and secret key, try using double
        quotes around all of your option values.</para>
      </important>

      <bridgehead>Taking a backup</bridgehead>

      <para>The following command will take a backup (without downloading it
      to your local PC), using backup profile #1:</para>

      <programlisting>php remote.phar --action=backup --host=http://www.example.com --secret=0Lsp-MjOSLvUL8VuM1h9T2zWfM4EGqMA --profile=1</programlisting>

      <para>You should see a long list of output coming through, detailing the
      backup progress. In the end it should read:</para>

      <screen>Backup finished successfully</screen>

      <para>And that's it! You now have a backup. Since it's useless without
      downloading, let's try...</para>

      <bridgehead>Taking and downloading a backup</bridgehead>

      <para>There are many ways to download a backup archive. We'll explore
      only two, using HTTP (not recommended on most sites) and FTP.</para>

      <para>First, let's try HTTP. The command line to achieve that is the
      same as the backup command line, with the --download, --dlmethod and
      --dlpath added:</para>

      <programlisting>php remote.phar --action=backup --host=http://www.example.com 
    --secret=0Lsp-MjOSLvUL8VuM1h9T2zWfM4EGqMA --profile=1
    --download --dlmode=http --dlpath="c:\Downloads"</programlisting>

      <warning>
        <para>The command line above should be entered ON A SINGLE LINE. We
        have added the line break for typesetting purposes only.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>This will take a backup and then download it to C:\Downloads (or
      anything else you specify with --dlpath) using the HTTP download method.
      After the "Backup finished successfully" messages you will also see many
      download lines and a "Archive downloaded successfully". If that fails,
      you'll have to use the FTP mode.</para>

      <para>First, you need to know the following information about your
      site:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>FTP hostname. We'll assume it's <uri>ftp.example.com</uri> for
          this example</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>FTP username and password. We'll assume it's
          <option>foo</option> and <option>bar</option>, respectively</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The FTP path to your backup output directory. We'll assume
          it's
          <filename>/public_html/administrator/components/com_akeeba/backup</filename>.</para>

          <tip>
            <para>In order to find this directory, connect to your site using
            FileZilla. Navigate inside the folder Joomla! is installed in.
            Usually it's a directory named <filename>public_html</filename>,
            <filename>htdocs</filename>, <filename>www</filename> or something
            similar. If unsure don't ask us, ask your host. Then navigate to
            your backup output directory. The default is
            <filename>administrators/components/com_akeeba/backup</filename>.
            If unsure, check your Akeeba Backup Configuration page. Now, on
            the right-hand pane you will find the FTP path, right above the
            folders list. Copy this; it's the path we need.</para>
          </tip>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Then, modify the command line to read:</para>

      <programlisting>php remote.phar --action=backup --host=http://www.example.com
--secret=0Lsp-MjOSLvUL8VuM1h9T2zWfM4EGqMA --profile=1
--download --dlmode=curl --dlpath="c:\Downloads"
--dlurl="ftp://<emphasis role="bold">foo</emphasis>:<emphasis role="bold">bar</emphasis>@<emphasis
          role="bold">ftp.example.com</emphasis>/<emphasis role="bold">public_html/administrator/components/com_akeeba/backup</emphasis>"</programlisting>

      <warning>
        <para>The command line above should be entered ON A SINGLE LINE. We
        have added the line break for typesetting purposes only.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>One final note. After you download the backup archive, it's a good
      idea to delete the copy on the server for security reasons. Just append
      --delete to the command line to achieve that. For example, the command
      line above will become:</para>

      <programlisting>php remote.phar --action=backup --host=http://www.example.com 
  --secret=0Lsp-MjOSLvUL8VuM1h9T2zWfM4EGqMA --profile=1
  --download --dlmode=curl --dlpath="c:\Downloads" --delete
  --dlurl="ftp://<emphasis role="bold">foo</emphasis>:<emphasis role="bold">bar</emphasis>@<emphasis
          role="bold">ftp.example.com</emphasis>/<emphasis role="bold">public_html/administrator/components/com_akeeba/backup</emphasis>"</programlisting>

      <warning>
        <para>The command line above should be entered ON A SINGLE LINE. We
        have added the line break for typesetting purposes only.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>That's it!</para>

      <bridgehead>Automating the whole lot</bridgehead>

      <para>If you want to automate updating Akeeba Backup, taking and
      downloading backups, you can simply create a batch/script file and use
      your Operating System's scheduling features to run it at predefined
      intervals. We suggest taking a look at the following tutorials:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><link
          xlink:href="http://www.cyberciti.biz/faq/how-do-i-add-jobs-to-cron-under-linux-or-unix-oses/">HowTo:
          Add Jobs To cron Under Linux or UNIX?</link></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link
          xlink:href="http://hints.macworld.com/article.php?story=2001020700163714">Using
          the 'cron' scheduler in Mac OS X</link></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link xlink:href="http://support.microsoft.com/kb/308569">How
          to schedule tasks on Windows XP</link></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><link
          xlink:href="http://windows.microsoft.com/en-US/windows7/Schedule-a-task">How
          to schedule tasks on Windows 7</link> (also works on Vista)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>As for the batch/script file, all you have to do is to include the
      commands above in a .BAT (Windows) or .sh (Linux, Mac OS X) file. For
      example, a Windows batch file (backup.bat) looks like that:</para>

      <programlisting>REM IMPORTANT! Before running Remote CLI, you have to change the current
REM directory to wherever remote.phar is located in. In this example, we
REM will assume that you followed our advice and put it in c:\PHP
C:
CD c:\PHP

REM The following line updates Akeeba Backup - REMOVE THE LINE BREAKS
REM WHEN COPYING THIS SCRIPT TO YOUR SYSTEM, OTHERWISE IT WILL NOT WORK!!!

php-cli.exe remote.phar --action=update --host=http://www.example.com
 --secret=iloveakeeba

REM The following line takes and downloads a backup - REMOVE THE LINE
REM BREAKS WHEN COPYING THIS SCRIPT TO YOUR SYSTEM, OTHERWISE IT WILL
REN NOT WORK!!!

php-cli.exe remote.phar --action=backup --host=http://www.example.com
 --secret=0Lsp-MjOSLvUL8VuM1h9T2zWfM4EGqMA --profile=1 --download
 --dlmode=curl --dlpath="c:\Downloads"
 --dlurl="ftp://foo:bar@ftp.example.com/public_html/administrator/components/com_akeeba/backup"
 --delete</programlisting>

      <para>Note that we assume that the path to PHP is c:\PHP\php-cli.exe and
      you followed our advice and also copied Remote CLI (remote.phar) into
      C:\PHP. That's it! You can now use the Scheduled Tasks feature of
      Windows to make this file run whenever you want, essentially having an
      always up-to-date copy of Akeeba Backup installed on your site, take
      automated backups of your site, download them to your PC and remove them
      from the server. All you need to do once you set this up is to remember
      to leave your PC turned on for the scheduled task to run. Easy
      peasy!</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
